Guide to the Emlen Etting Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Emlen Etting papers
1924-1982
YCAL MSS 645
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.42
(3 boxes)
The Emlen Etting Papers contain correspondence, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs that document the professional and personal life of visual artist Emlen Etting. The papers span the years 1924 to 1982.
Etting, Emlen, 1905-1993
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on The Bradford F. and Lila L. Swan Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Printed material received with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
Emlen Etting (1905-1993)
Emlen Etting, American poet, painter, sculptor, illustrator, and filmmaker.
Scope and Contents
The Emlen Etting Papers contain correspondence, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs that document the professional and personal life of visual artist Emlen Etting. The papers span the years 1924 to 1982.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1924-1957. II.Correspondence, 1927-1976. III. Other Papers, 1940-1982.
Artists -- United States -- Archives; Illustrators -- United States -- Archives; Painters -- United States -- Archives; Poets -- United States -- Archives; Photographs -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century -- Archives; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th Century; Painters -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Etting, Emlen, 1905-1993
- Writings, 1924-1957, undated; Series I; 12
  Scope and Contents
  Contains typescript and autograph manuscript drafts of writings by Etting. Unidentified writings are filed at the end of the series.
  - Chateau de Feuilles, handwritten draft, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mixing Memory and Desire, typescript draft and related notes and correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Paddling Down the Moselle, typescript draft, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poems, handwritten drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Poems for Travelers, handwritten draft, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Studio in Paris, typescript draft, photocopy, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Voyage de Peintre, handwritten draft, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Various writings, handwritten and typescript drafts, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Correspondence, 1927-1976; Series II; 26
  - A-Z, 1927-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13-36)
  - Berman, Avis, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Crosby, Caresse, 1930-1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Force, Julianna, 1935-1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters from Anthology Film Archive, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Other Papers, 1940-1982, undated; Series III; 24
  Contains photographs of Etting and others, postcards, artwork by Etting and others, printed materials, and other papers.
  - Photographs
    - Etting, Emlen, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 57)
    - Etting, Ellen, 1940-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Etting, Ellen, 1940-1972, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 58-59)
    - Etting, Gloria, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Etting, Gloria, 1977, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 60)
    - Art by Etting, undated (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
    - [Damorsch, Walter], undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - McDermott, Keith, 1976 December (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Siegel, Adrian, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Includes artwork by Siegel
    - "Phoenix Rising" photographs and articles, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Unidentified woman smoking a cigarette, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 61)
    - Unidentified running boy, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 62)
    - Unidentified boy in a uniform, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Various postcards and photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Artwork
    - Five sketches and watercolors by Emlen Etting, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 63)
    - Sketch, with related letter, by Julius Thiengen Block, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Lithographs by Alexander Portnoff, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 64-65)
    - Sketches and watercolors, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Notebook, "Emlen Etting III. M. R. B. A. P. O. 403", 1944 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Tear sheets, exhibit catalogs, clippings, 1936-1980 (Box 2, Folder 54-54a)
  - Tear sheets, exhibit catalogs, clippings, 1936-1980 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Clippings used for art reference, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "Voyage to Cythera," attributed to Robert Morse, typescript draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)